Horst Frenz papers, 1905-1985 C367
Indiana University Archives
Horst Frenz papers
1871-1990
1940-1980
Indiana University Archives
Frenz, Horst, 1912-1990
C367
3.4 cubic feet 3 rc and 1 dc
Horst Frenz was a professor in the Department of Comparative Literature and English at Indiana University from 1940-1981, and served as chair of the Comparative Literature department from its creation in 1949 until 1977. The collection consists of publications, correspondence, and records relating to Frenz's position at IU as well as his professional interests. There is some correspondence relating to the establishment of the Dept. of Comparative Literature.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required for access.
Biographical Note
Born June 29, 1912, in Oberlauringen, Germany, Horst Frenz attended the University of Goettingen, where he received his Ph.D. in English in 1936. Frenz moved to the United States in 1938 to attend the University of Illinois receiving a MA in 1939.
Frenz came to I.U. in 1940 as an instructor in English, was promoted to assistant professor of world literature in 1945, associate professor in 1949, and full professor in 1954. Frenz retired in 1981. In 1949, Frenz helped establish the Comparative Literature program at IU, and he served as the first chairman from 1949 to 1977. In addition to these duties, in 1964 Dr. Frenz was named associate director of the School of Letters. Under the direction of Frenz, the Comparative Literature program was one of the first in the world to incorporate Asian-Western relations and an interdisciplinary approach into the curriculum.
Outside of IU, Frenz served as the president of the American Comparative Literature Association from 1971-1974, and president of the International Comparative Literature Association from 1973-1976. Frenz was the recipient of Fulbright, Ford Foundation and Guggenheim Foundation fellowships, and he served as Editor of the Yearbook of Comparative and General Literature. In addition to authoring Die Entwicklung des Sozialen Dramas in England vor Galsworthy in 1938, Frenz published and co-edited numerous articles in the fields of drama, comparative literature and American literature. Frenz died on November 17, 1990 in Bloomington.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: Publications and writings, Correspondence, Professional activity and Subject files.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Horst Frenz span the years of 1905-1990 and are organized into four series; Publications and writings, Correspondence, Professional activity and Subject files.
The first series, Publications and writings (1938-1988), comprises the bulk of the collection and contains notes, drafts, and published copies of Frenz's written works. It is arranged chronologically by date of publication, though there are many undated items that have been arranged alphabetically by title or subject at the end of the series. Prominent subjects in these publications include comparative literature and playwrights and authors such as Eugene O'Neill, Thornton Wilder, and Thomas Wolf, and Walt Whitman.
The second series, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically and contains professional correspondence dated 1935-1990. Much of the correspondence relates to publications, research, professional organizations, and academic discussions of topics related to comparative literature. Individuals and organizations with whom Frenz corresponded repeatedly have been grouped together. Some of the prominent correspondents include Hans Joachim Lang, Gyorgy Vajda, and Istvan Soter, the president of the International Comparative Literature Assocation from 1970-1973. Other letters that represent one time correspondence have been organized by year in the folders titled "General Correspondence."
The third series, Professional activity, contains materials from the years 1938-1990. These materials pertain to many aspects of Frenz's career, such as research, publications, lectures, and organizations in which Frenz was involved. Examples of materials in this series include typed copies of addresses given by Frenz, information on his grant projects, flyers and programs for his lectures, and reviews of his publications.
The Subject files series spans the years 1905-1989 and is arranged alphabetically by folder heading. It contains a variety of materials related to Frenz's activities at Indiana University and his areas of interest. Included in this series are items pertaining to the American Comparative Literature Association and the International Comparative Literature Association, both organizations in which Frenz served as president. There are also many items about Indiana University in general and I.U.'s Comparative Literature department.
Separated Material
Copies of publications not by Frenz have been removed.
13 photographs have been pulled and transferred to the University Archives Photograph Collection. Some of these are of Horst Frenz, others are of Frenz's professional contacts and authors and playwrights.
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 7282, 2010/048
Provenance
Deposited in the Archives by Mrs. Frenz, December 1984. Additions sent to the Archives in 2010 by Howard Swyers of the Dept. of Comparative Literature.
Literature teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; English teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Frenz, Horst, 1912-1990 -- Archives; Frenz, Horst, 1912-1990 -- Correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Comparative Literature -- History -- 20th century -- Sources
- Publications and writings, 1871-1988; undated; 1938-1988 (Box 1)
  - "Rudolf Schmidt to Whitman" and "Rolleston to Whitman" Letter drafts, 1871-1884 (Box 1)
  - "Die Entwicklung des sozialen Dramas in England vor Galsworthy," draft and published copy, 1938 (Box 1)
  - "Thornton Wilder: Our Town in Germany", 1946 (Box 1)
  - "Bayard Taylor and the Reception of Goethe in America," published copy, 1942 (Box 1)
  - "The German Drama in the Middle West," draft and published copy, 1942 (Box 1)
  - "Edwin Booth in Polyglot Shakespeare Performances," draft and published copy, 1943 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill in Russia," published copy, 1943 (Box 1)
  - "Campbell's My Partner in Berlin," published copy, 1944 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill in France," published copy, 1944 (Box 1)
  - "Johannes V. Jenson," draft and published copy, 1944 (Box 1)
  - "O'Neill Collections I Have Seen," reprint, 1945 (Box 1)
  - "The Stage History of Shelley's The Cenci," drafts, 1945; undated (Box 1)
  - "William Gillette on the London Stage," draft and reprint, 1945 (Box 1)
  - "Georg Kaiser," published copy, 1946 (Box 1)
  - "Karl Knortz, Interpreter of American Literature and Culture," published copy, 1946 (Box 1)
  - "Anderson and Stalling's 'What Price Glory?' And Carl Zuckmayer's 'Rivalen'", 1946; 1961 (Box 1)
  - "Anderson and Stalling's 'What Price Glory' and Carl Zuckmayer's 'Rivalen'", 1947 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill on the London Stage," drafts and published copy, 1947 (Box 1)
  - "Walt Whitman's Letters to Karl Knortz," drafts and reprint, 1948 (Box 1)
  - "Evolution of a World Literature Course," reprint, 1950 (Box 1)
  - "Some Notes on the Play," draft and published copy, 1952 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill on the German Stage," draft and published copy, 1953 (Box 1)
  - "Thomas Wolfe als Dramatiker," published copy, 1953 (Box 1)
  - "The Art of Translation", 1956 (Box 1)
  - "Bayard Taylor's German Lecture on American Literature," reprint, 1956 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill in Deutschland," reprint, 1956 (Box 1)
  - "Teaching Comparative Arts: A Challenge," published copy, 1956 (Box 1)
  - "Thornton Wilder's Visits to Postwar Germany", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "Thornton Wilder's Reception in Germany", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "St. John Irvine On Eugene O'Neill," reprint, 1959 (Box 1)
  - "Notes of Eugene O'Neill in Japan", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "The Reception of Thornton Wilder's Plays in Germany," drafts and reprint, 1960 (Box 1)
  - "Tennessee Williams and His German Critics," reprint, 1960 (Box 1)
  - "American Playwrights and the German Psyche," drafts and published copy, 1961 (Box 1)
  - "Amerikanische Dramaturgie," drafts, 1961-1962; undated (Box 1)
  - "Thornton Wilder", 1961 (Box 1)
  - "Wechselbeziehung zwischen dem deutschen und amerikanischen Theater," draft, 1961 (Box 1)
  - "Comparative Literature Method and Perspective," reprint, 1962 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill's 'Desire under the Elms' and Henrik Ibsen's 'Rosmersholm'," published copy, 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Nationalism and Cosmopolitanism in American Letters: A Backward Glance," published copy, 1964 (Box 1)
  - "A Note on Ibsen and O'Neil," draft, 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Einleitung" and "Lehrjahre" drafts and correspondence, 1965 (Box 1)
  - "Yearbook of Comparative and General Literature," published copy, 1965 (Box 1)
  - "More Shakespeare and Less Aeschylus," drafts and reprint, 1966 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill and the Royal Dramatic Theatre of Stockholm," reprint, 1967 (Box 1)
  - "Comparative Literature Today," reprint, 1971 (Box 1)
  - "Amerikanische Dramatiker," published copy, 1973 (Box 1)
  - "College of Arts of the University of Riyadh," draft, 1975 (Box 1)
  - "Comparative Literature Today," reprint, 1976 (Box 1)
  - "East-West Literary Relations: Outside Looking In," reprint, 1976 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill, a Contemporary American Playwright," published copy, 1976 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill and China," reprint, 1979 (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill and the European Connection," published copy, 1979 (Box 1)
  - "Three Decades of Comparative Literature," published copy, 1980 (Box 1)
  - "Marco Millions," published copy, 1981 (Box 1)
  - "The Good German," unpublished final version, 1988 (Box 1)
  - "Adolescence and 'Cat on a Hot Tin Roof'", undated (Box 1)
  - "Alexander Tairov and the 1930 World Tour of the Kamerny Theater," draft and published copy, undated (Box 1)
  - "Alfred Nobel's 'Explosive' Prize and World Literature," drafts, undated (Box 1)
  - "American Dramatists on the Stage and before the Theater Critics of the Federal Republic," drafts, undated (Box 1)
  - "Amerikanische Dramatiker auf den Bühnen und vor der Theaterkritik der Bundesrepublik, 19451965", undated (Box 1)
  - "Amerikanische Dichter und Dichtkunst,"drafts, undated (Box 1)
  - "Appreciation of Drama", undated (Box 1)
  - "Berkley Campbell's My Partner in Berlin", undated (Box 1)
  - Böll, Heinrich, miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 1)
  - "Comments on Thomas Wolfe", undated (Box 1)
  - "Comparative Literature for Undergraduates," reprint, undated (Box 1)
  - "Drama," draft, undated (Box 1)
  - "The English Social Problem Play from the French Revolution to Galsworthy," draft, undated (Box 1)
  - "Eugene O'Neill and the Modern Drama," draft, undated (Box 1)
  - "From Ibsen to O'Neill: Cultural Ties between the Old and New Worlds," draft, undated (Box 1)
  - "From O'Neill to Albee," draft, undated (Box 1)
  - "Georg Kaiser", undated (Box 1)
  - "German Criticism of American Drama," published copy, undated (Box 1)
  - Göttingens berühmle Amerikaner, undated (Box 1)
  - Hauptmann, Gerhardt, miscellaneous writings, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - "History of Comparative Literature at Indiana University", undated (Box 2)
  - "Horst Frenz and John Hess: American Literature in the German Republic," drafts, undated (Box 2)
  - "Introduction" Gerhart Hauptmann draft, undated (Box 2)
  - "Long Day's Journey into Night: The First Performance," published copy, undated (Box 2)
  - Mann, Thomas, miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 2)
  - "Maxwell Anderson in Post-War Germany," draft, undated (Box 2)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    3 folders
  - "Nationales und Übernationales in der Amerikanische Literatur," draft, undated (Box 2)
  - "Nobel Lectures," draft, undated (Box 2)
  - "Nobelpreis und Weltliterature,"published copy, undated (Box 2)
  - "North American Drama and the Western Stage," drafts, undated (Box 2)
  - "A Note on Poetic Drama: Anderson, T.S. Eliot, Archibald MacLeish," draft, undated (Box 2)
  - "O'Neill, Eugene, miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 2)
  - "Preface," reprint, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Novel," draft, undated (Box 2)
  - Obwohl auf den ersten Blick" draft, undated (Box 2)
  - Original Notes plus appendix A and B – n, undated (Box 2)
  - "A Present Day View of Eugene O'Neill's Dramatic Work," draft, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Reception of Contemporary American Literature" drafts, undated (Box 2)
  - "Schiller", undated (Box 2)
  - Shaw, George Bernard, miscellaneous writings, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - "Some Notes", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Stage History of Shelley's The Cenci", undated (Box 2)
  - Tennessee Williams and His German Critics, undated; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - "Thomas Wolfe's Mannerhouse on the German Stage", drafts, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - "Thornton Wilder und Deutschland," drafts, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Thornton Wilder and Germany, undated (Box 2)
  - "Tragedy", undated (Box 2)
  - Untitled drafts, undated (Box 2)
  - Various essay drafts, undated (Box 2)
  - Whitman and Rolleston: A Correspondence, drafts and notes, undated; (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Whitman, Walt, miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 2)
  - Wilder, Thornton, miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1935-1990; undated
  - Bruck, Jan, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
  - Comparative Literature Program inquiries, undated (Box 2)
  - Dana, H.W.L., 1945-1947 (Box 2)
  - Deutsche Gesellschaft für Amerikastudien, 1989 (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1935-59; (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1960-1969; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1970-1979; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1980-1990 (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 2)
  - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Hatfield, W. Wilber, 1943-47 (Box 2)
  - Hawari, Rida, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Japan Foundation, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Kery, Laszlo, 1971; 1974 (Box 2)
  - Kretzoi, Charlotte, 1971; 1975 (Box 2)
  - Kunst, Arthur E., 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Lang, Hans Joachim, 1962-1973; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Levin, Harry, 1948-1971 (Box 3)
  - Pochmann, Henry, 1952-1958 (Box 3)
  - Remak, Henry, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Reprints, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
  - Sachithanden, Vaithinathaswami, 1963-1968 (Box 3)
  - Söter, Istvan, 1965-1974 (Box 3)
  - Sutton, Joseph L., 1961-1966 (Box 3)
  - Tairov, Alexander, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Thompson, Ewa, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
  - Tsukimura, Reiko, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Vajda, Gyorgy M., 1972-1977 (Box 3)
- Professional activity, 1938-1990; undated
  - Actes du VII Congrès de l'Association Internationale de Littèrature Comparee - Opening Address invitation, undated (Box 3)
  - Address to the American (ACLA), undated (Box 3)
  - Address at Attila University, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Address to the Third Annual Meeting of the International Comparative Literature Association (ICLA), undated (Box 3)
  - American Comparative Literature Association Report on Professional Standards, undated (Box 3)
  - American Contributions to the Cultural Life of the Occupied Areas (study project), undated (Box 3)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, undated (Box 3)
  - American Philosophical Society Grants, 1962; 1979 (Box 3)
  - Area and Language Studies reports, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1939-1990 (Box 3)
  - Comparative Literature and the Arts Grant Project, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Contract for "Writers of the Western World, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Delta Phi Alpha certificate, 1939 (Box 3)
  - English 501 The Technical Vocabulary of Literary Scholarship, undated (Box 3)
  - Eugene O'Neill-World Dramatist Grant Project, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Faculty workload, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - German Area Course, undated (Box 3)
  - Graduate school research, 1945-1950 (Box 3)
  - Indiana University Board of Trustees recognition, 1981; undated (Box 3)
  - Indiana University Comparative Literature Dept. Faculty Annual Report, 1942-1966 (Box 3)
    - 1942-1947 (Box 3)
    - 1959-1966 (Box 3)
  - Lecture publicity, 1939-1980 (Box 3)
  - National Humanities Center Fellowship Selection Announcement, 1979 (Box 3)
  - NEH Curriculum Grant, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Newberry Library Conference on American Studies, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Resumé, undated (Box 3)
  - Reviews, 1940-1984; undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1940-59 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1961-1984; undated (Box 3)
    - Whitman and Rolleston: A Correspondence, 1951-1954 (Box 3)
  - Seminar Description, From Ibsen to Albee: A Comparative Approach to the American and European Drama, undated (Box 3)
  - United States Educational Commission Germany Fulbright, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Updating of Ph.D. graduate listing, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Military Institute Appointment Announcement, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Visiting Lectureship, University of Szeged, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Wisconsin, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Witman and Rolleston reviews and correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 3)
- Subject Files, 1905-1989; undated
  - ACLA (American Comparative Literature Association), 1962-1977 (Box 3)
  - A.V., Lunacharsky, undated (Box 3)
  - Baynard Taylor bibliography, undated (Box 3)
  - A Bibliography of Critical Writings on the Drama of August Strindberg, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Bibliography of the Department of English, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Busch, William, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Bibliography of the Department of English, undated (Box 3)
  - College English, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Das Rathaus in Hamburg, undated (Box 3)
  - Dreiser, Theodore, undated (Box 3)
  - Entrace papers under Lewy, undated (Box 3)
  - Exhibition program, 1935-1961 (Box 3)
  - Gerhart Hauptmann's "The Weavers" flyer, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Gilette, William, 1905; 1940; undated (Box 3)
  - Herman Hesse, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Home is a Foreign Country, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Ibsen, undated (Box 3)
  - Indiana University, 1940-1949; 1961; 1981 (Box 3)
  - Indiana University Comparative Literature, 1949-1980; undated (Box 4)
  - International Comparative Literature Association, 1961-1989 (Box 4)
  - Matei Calinescu CV, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Moravia, Alberto, undated (Box 4)
  - NDEA (National Defense Education Act) Title IV, 1962-1965 (Box 4)
  - Naturalization, 1940-1948; undated (Box 4)
  - Photocopy of "Mourning becomes Electra" notes, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Playwright and the Atomic World," by Arthur Miller, undated (Box 4)
  - Report of the Mucia Team to the University of Riyadh, 1975; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - "Saturday Review of Literature", 1949 (Box 4)
  - Schnitzler, Arthur, 1951; undated (Box 4)
  - Shaw, George Bernard, 1956; undated (Box 4)
  - Tennessee Williams, 1947 (Box 4)
  - The Theatre Annual, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Theatre Kamerny program, undated (Box 4)
  - Twelfth Newberry Library Conference on American Studies, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Walt Whitman Bibliography, undated (Box 4)
  - Welleck, Rene, 1962-1973 (Box 4)